Alex.Kosykh.Job@gmail.com

1-425-802-7731

Summary

Enterprise Architect and Delivery Manager specializing in Data Integration, Data Warehousing and Big Data Management with 20+ years of experience leading IT innovation and facilitating business development for Fortune 500 companies - Symetra, Expedia, Microsoft, Unisys, EMC Corporation, Verizon, small and start-up businesses.

Distinguishing qualities:

- practicing and certified Enterprise IT Architect (TOGAF)
- ~ entrepreneurial vision of IT capabilities and knowledge of several industries
- ~ expert level knowledge of all phases of Software Development Life Cycle
- broad knowledge of various platforms and technology stacks (MS, IBM, Linux)
- expert level programming skills (C#, Python, VB, T-SQL, PowerShell)
- strong project manager and SCRUM master
- seasoned delivery leader with proven successful track of managing global teams and projects with budgets exceeding \$15mln
- passionate about new ways of taming world data and discovering new knowledge

Specialties:

- Large scale Data Integration solutions utilizing broad range of vendor and open source technologies, services, and products
- ~ Data analysis and Business Intelligence solutions (real-time analytics, dashboards, statistics)
- extensive knowledge of DB technologies (MS SQL, Azure, Oracle, Hadoop, MongoDB, Cassandra, Apache Flume, Spark, Pig Hive, ORM, OData)
- ~ Data Warehousing EDW, ODS, Data Vault, Data Lake, "real-time" ELT/ETL, data governance
- ~ Integration of Enterprise with CRM, ERP and MDM solutions
- Project management (PMI, RUP, SCRUM, Kanban)

Education and Certifications

B.Sc., Applied Math and Statistics
 Microsoft Certified Solution Developer
 TIL

Key skills

Enterprise Architecture Practice
 BI Solutions and Data analysis

Database design, DW implementation
 Custom ETL/ELT

MS SQL, Hadoop, Mongo DB, Oracle
 SQL, OLAP, MapReduce

Project Management, SCRUM Master
 Systems Integration

NET, C#, PowerShell, SQL, Python
 Operations Intelligence

Experience

Symetra

Enterprise Architect 09 / 2014 – Present

As a member of Enterprise Architecture team I fulfill broad range of functions bridging governance of Enterprise IT and daily operational needs of Group Benefits business division.

- I enjoy working on strategic projects and define road maps of IT capabilities evolution, define architecture and ensure compliance of ongoing projects with Symetra IT and Security policies, battle to improve architecture and operational maturity of existing systems, participate in projects delivery and operational issues troubleshooting.
- On a daily basis I learn to speak the language and appreciate points of view of diverse groups of partners and customers - Symetra IT and Group Benefits business leadership; partners and vendors facilitating Data Centers and systems operations; project delivery teams and business stakeholders.
- I am proud to deliver for and be part of key Enterprise projects Data Center migration, Windows 2003 migration, Operational Analytics and network traffic analysis, development of OData services (C#, SQL) and Data Integration strategy, full-stack scalability troubleshooting, 1-3 years IT strategies and capability road maps, data monitoring tools (Python and PowerShell).

Symetra also helped me to obtain my TOGAF and ITIL certifications, which I directly employ while working on definition and implementation of new IT processes.

Expedia, Inc.

Senior Architect 05 / 2009 - 09 / 2014

While switching between and combining roles of Data Architect and IT Product Manager I had privilege to work with several groups enabling complex machinery of Expedia global online business operations.

- Expedia provided me with a great opportunity to experience scale and complexity of modern Internet-based Online Travel industry leader tightly interacting with a web of travel-related businesses. Dynamic environment where "business solution" sometimes may mean that code change needs to be ready by next morning.
- Working as Data Architect I led several initiatives and projects, such as leading Data Governance practices and Architecture Working Groups, design of new generation Data Development tools and processes enabling in-place database update of Expedia mission critical systems.
- During implementation of "near real-time" ETL system for Expedia EDW I managed distributed solution team integrating a number of NOSQL technologies (Cassandra, MongoDB, Hadoop, Pig, Hive) with traditional DB systems (MS SQL and DB2).

- I initiated development and led implementation of several products enabling real-time audit of data consistency across multiple business division DBs and audit BI tool facilitating timely detection of financial data discrepancies.
- I helped Finance IT to develop unified solution for collecting financial data from globally distributed Expedia partners, vendors, and customers leveraging industry standards (OAGIS) and integrating data in Oracle EBS, line of homegrown financial products, and EDW.

Unisys

Architect 01 / 2008 - 03 / 2009

As member of Unisys Application Modernization solutions team with focus on Microsoft technologies I worked on design of reusable solution patterns and project start-up kits. Building full stack customer-centric prototypes using variety of Microsoft products (SQL Server, SharePoint, BizTalk), custom and 3rd party components.

The employment was terminated due to radical staff reduction in wake of Economic Crisis of 2008.

Microsoft

Senior Program Manager 03 / 2006 - 11 / 2007

I had a privilege to play my role in globally distributed Microsoft team partnering with Qwest Communications to materialize a "Unified Communication" scenarios by bridging land-line voice mails with Hotmail and allowing Hotmail users listen and read voicemails received by a home answering machine.

The product technology stack included voicemail audio transcoding, real-time distributed message processing, speech-to-text translation, keyword detection, Hotmail integration.

As Program Manager I worked with diverse group of stakeholders and was responsible for product definition and delivery, technical specifications, project schedule execution.

- Lead Windows Live Voicemail tri-continental project team through full cycle of product delivery - from inception to initial release and number of version upgrades
- Developed and maintained partnership with Microsoft teams (Hotmail, Research, Office,
 Ops) coordinating collaborative efforts and feature priorities
- ~ Developed and owned product definition, architecture, and requirements
- Served as SCRUM Master for the team of 20 engineers

GRT Corporation

Senior Consultant 09 / 1998 - 03 / 2006

Working as Sr. Consultant in a rapidly growing company during the "Internet boom" years gave me great opportunity to understand what 'good solution' means for problems in broad range of scenarios – from 2-3 week engagements to 2+ years projects for world leading companies.

During these years I had to learn new technologies on the spot, play every role in software engineering team, and support business development process of a growing consulting company.

My clients included such notable names as Verizon, GE Finance, Teradyne and number of medium and small businesses.

Major projects - Architect of real-time data warehouse of geo-spatial data for major telecom - 2 years, team of 25 - Intranet and

public customer service web portal for major electronic manufacturer - 1 year, team of 7 - Architect and lead developer of rapid Business Intelligence prototyping tool using schemaless data model and OLAP technologies.